Finding aid to the Heather Huyck papers SSC.MS.00505
Sophia Smith Collection
Heather Huyck papers
1935-2017
Sophia Smith Collection
Huyck, Heather
SSC.MS.00505
43.5 linear feet (35 record cartons)
The Heather Huyck papers consist of research files for Huyck's dissertation,"To Celebrate a Whole Priesthood: The History of Women's Ordination in the Episcopal Church" and professional and personal papers related to her career as a public historian, working especially with the National Parks Service to establish women's history sites. Also includes papers related to Huyck's mother, Dorothy Boyle Huyck, who was involved with the Family Camping Association in the 1960s and 1970s.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Accruals
This collection is comprised of the following accessions, some of which may not have accession records. Accession numbers: 04S-59. Accessions were received on the following dates: 2004-09-09.
Accruals
Periodic accruals to collection are expected.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Heather Huyck has donated her papers in two accessions, one in 2004 (04S-59) and one in 2017 (2017-S-0066).
Biographical Note
Heather Ann Huyck graduated cum laude from Carleton College in 1973. She went on to earn an M.A. in cultural anthropology (1978) and a Ph.D. in American history (1981) from the University of Minnesota. She founded Minnesota Women's Ordination Now in 1974, and was active in the organization until 1978. Huyck began working for the National Park Service in 1971, as a college student, and has been employed by that agency in various capacities since then. As a cultural anthropologist and as a historian, Huyck was responsible for"the interpretation of cultural resources (historical and anthropological)"at numerous NPS sites from 1978 to 1983, including Ellis Island, the Women's Rights National Historical Park, and the Clara Barton National Historic Site. She also worked in the U. S. Congress on legislation and related issues pertaining to NPS sites, from 1983 to 1994. Since 1994 Huyck has headed the NPS's Office of Strategic Planning, and from 2002 to 2017 she was also regional chief historian and visiting lecturer in American Studies at the College of William and Mary. She has also served as president of the National Collaborative for Women's History Sites, an organization she co-founded.
Dorothy Boyle Huyck, born in Madison, Wisconsin, graduated from Carleton College in Northfield, Minnesota. She moved to Washington, DC in 1946 and worked for the US State Department asa liason officer in agricultural agencies until 1951. Boyle Huyck later served as a consultant on family camping to the National Park Service from 1962-1967 and as a freelance writer published several articles on conservation and travel. At the time of her death in 1979, she was writing a history of women in the Park Service where she also served as a contract worker.
Scope and Contents
The first accession of the Heather Huyck Papers consisted of research files for Huyck's dissertation,"To Celebrate a Whole Priesthood: The History of Women's Ordination in the Episcopal Church."Includes interviews with women involved in the church. Materials pertaining to Women's Ordination Now are also included. Some documents in the accession post-date the dissertation.
The second accession includes professional and personal papers related to Heather Huyck's career as a public historian, working especially with the National Parks Service to establish women's history sites. Also includes papers related to Huyck's mother, Dorothy Boyle Huyck, involved with the Family Camping Association in the 1960s and 1970s.
Other Finding Aids
This online finding aid currently provides detailed description of only the most recent additions to this collection. Additional materials are described in unpublished lists that can be sent to you upon request by contacting specialcollections@smith.edu
Episcopal Church--Clergy--History--Sources; Ordination of women--Episcopal Church--History--Sources; Bibliographies; Books; Brochures; articles; clippings; correspondence; notebooks; Notes; Interviews; Newspapers; Pamphlets; Videotapes; Women's history; Huyck, Dorothy Boyle; National Park Service; Huyck, Heather; Huyck, Heather
- Heather Huyck and Dorothy Boyle Huyck professional and personal papers, 1935-2017; 2017-S-0066; 27.5 linear feet (22 record cartons)
  Scope and Contents
  Professional and personal papers related to Heather Huyck's career as a public historian, working especially with the National Parks Service to establish women's history sites. Also includes papers related to Huyck's mother, Dorothy Boyle Huyck, involved with the Family Camping Association in the 1960s and 1970s.
  Videotapes
  - National Park Service studies and Women's Rights XHPX: Correspondence, photographs, writings, articles, newsletters, pamphlets, journals, notes and papers relating to women's issues and the National Park Service, 1976-2011 (Box 1)
  - National Park Service Women's Conference and Jamestown National Park, including memos, correspondence, photographs, educational materials and papers, agendas, participant materials, and published/press materials, 1979-2002 (Box 2)
  - Journals, teaching materials, graduate school application materials and correspondence, graduate school notes and papers, government work correspondence, and published materials, 1965-2004 (Box 3)
  - Teaching materials, National Park Service materials, and Organization of American Historians lecturer series papers, 1975-2009 (Box 4)
  - National Park Service papers, biographical materials and notes, published articles and papers, testimonies and correspondence for various Congressional Subcommittees re: National Parks and Public Lands and representing women's history, 1974-2011 (Box 5)
  - Legislation, National Park Service and National Council on Public History (NCPH) materials, including correspondence and reports, 1961-2000 (Box 6)
  - Congressional committee notes, National Park Service VHS cassettes, biographical materials and correspondence, 1990-2017 (Box 7)
    Work daytimers and calendars (1995-1997); Congressional notebook; San Antonio Missions/HR 4811 pamphlets, photographs and papers (1990); GPRA on the GD booklet; Acadian Culture/S 1756 (1990); NPS audio/visual VHS cassettes (undated, 1993-1997); biographical materials and correspondence (1995-2016); miscellaneous conference name tags (undated, 2003-2017)
  - Biographical materials, including correspondence, research notes and dissertation drafts, 1962-2002 (Box 8)
  - Dorothy Boyle Huyck's Camp Fire Girls handbooks (1935-1936); National Park Service proposals and brochures; "Weaving the Fabric of American History" seminar syllabus and readings, 1935-2003 (Box 9)
  - Historians on the Hill papers and materials related to the National Park Service, including periodicals, correspondence, and reports, 1963-2005 (Box 10)
  - National Park Service: testimonies; notes and biographical materials; reports and published materials related to Jamestown and women, 1955-2006 (Box 11)
  - Course work and teaching materials, including notes and syllabi, 1974-2011 (Box 12)
  - College of William and Mary course work and conference papers, 1980-2004 (Box 13)
  - National Park Service major projects: brochures, correspondence, conference papers, and notes, 1985-2010 (Box 14)
  - National Park Service/Jamestown Women's Leadership project: papers, memos, correspondence, reports, notes, pamphlets and brochures, 1974-2005 (Box 15)
  - Teaching American History papers and Early American Sites Network papers, 1960-2005 (Box 16)
  - Subcommittee on Civil Service and American Society of Landscape Architecture papers, 1974-1993 (Box 17)
  - Journals; miscellaneous periodicals and pamphlets, 1962-2005 (Box 18)
  - Teach American History grant materials, 2003-2004 (Box 19)
  - Correspondence, 1981-1986 (Box 19)
  - Dorothy Boyle Huyck correspondence, published and unpublished papers, and biographical materials, 1955-1976 (Box 20)
  - Dorothy Boyle Huyck research materials: notes and correspondence, 1962-1981 (Box 21)
  - Dorothy Boyle Huyck American Camping Association/Family Camping Federation: correspondence, research notes, reports, and brochures, 1962-1976 (Box 22)